Finding Aid for Camp Filibert Roth (University of Michigan) Records 1928-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Camp Filibert Roth (University of Michigan) records 1928-1987
Camp Filibert Roth (University of Michigan)
1 oversize folder
1 oversize v
7.0 linear feet
Summer training camp for University of Michigan forestry students. Correspondence, memoranda, and other materials concerning the operation of the camp; include correspondence of Robert Craig, Jr. and Samuel T. Dana; material collected by camp director John Carrow which relates to the camp and School of Natural Resources; and photographs and scrapbooks.
8737 Bimu C367 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred by the School of Natural Resources (Donor No. 1887 ) in various accessions.
The records are open for research.
Camp Filibert Roth was opened in 1929 in Iron County, Michigan, as a summer field experience camp for students in the University of Michigan's School of Natural Resources. The camp was named for Professor Filibert Roth (1858-1925), founder of the School of Forestry at the University of Michigan and a leader in the field of forestry. From his arrival at the University in 1903, Roth guided the program until his retirement in 1923 at which time he was appointed Professor Emeritus. To his colleagues and students, Roth was known affectionately as "Daddy."
Prior to 1929, forestry students had been required to spend the summer between their sophomore and junior years doing surveying work at Camp Davis on Douglas Lake. The decision by the Department of Civil Engineering to relocate Camp Davis to Wyoming and the desire of the School of Forestry to have a camp located in Michigan's Upper Peninsula devoted to forestry training prompted the school in 1928 to begin investigating possible locations for a camp.
From 1929 to 1935, the camp was located temporarily at an old logging camp near Munising while a permanent location was sought. In 1935, the camp moved to its permanent location on Golden Lake near Beechwood, Michigan. The curriculum at Camp Filibert Roth combined academic and practical skills in a three-month summer session in the woods of the Upper Peninsula. Timber management classes, fire fighting skills, and harvesting techniques were required of all upper division forestry majors. With the retirement of the camp's resident manager in 1987, activities at the camp ceased. Thereafter, the camp was only utilized occasionally by graduate student researchers. Camp Filibert Roth was sold by the university in 1994.
Additional information relating to the history of Camp Filibert Roth and its activities can be found within the record group University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
The records of Camp Filibert Roth document the administration of the camp and the range of research, training and recreational acclivities that took place there. Records include topical and correspondence files of camp directors and School of Natural Resources faculty who worked with the camp, photographs and slides of camp facilities and activities, correspondence with camp alumni and printed material.
The records were received in two principal accessions. Boxes 1-2 were acquired from the School of Natural Resources. The second accession, boxes 3-7, consists largely of the material collected by John Carrow (1913-1995), a former student and professor in the School of Natural Resources. Carrow graduated from the University of Michigan in 1938 and joined the Faculty in 1947. He was also Director of Camp Filibert Roth from 1948 to 1967. Carrow was Secretary of the School of Natural Resources Alumni Association and continued to hold that position after his retirement as a full professor in 1977. Carrow collected items of historical interest not only from Camp Filibert Roth but also from the entire School of Natural Resources.
The records are organized into eight series: Topical Files, Chronological Files, Printed Materials, Alumni Association, Camp Files, Midwest Forestry Conclave, School of Natural Resources and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Camp Filibert Roth (University of Michigan); Carrow, John, 1913-1995.; Forest management.; Forestry schools and education--Michigan.; Forests and forestry--Michigan.; Logging.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alger County (Mich.); Beaver Lake (Alger County, Mich.); Camp Filibert Roth (University of Michigan); Golden Lake (Mich.); Grand Island (Alger County, Mich.); Iron County (Mich.); University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan--Students.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Craig, Robert, 1882-1962.; Dana, Samuel Trask, 1883-1978
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (.2 linear ft.) is arranged alphabetically and includes such materials as histories of the camp, annual reports, and documentation of the School of Natural Resources' search for a permanent site for the camp.
  - Histories (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports by Camp Director
    - 1939-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1958-1986 (Box 1)
  - Bank Account Books (three) 1945-1956, 1962-1963, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Dining Hall Plans 1949 (Box 1)
  - Proposed Camp Sites
    - Beaver Lake (Alger Co.) 1928-1935 (Box 1)
    - Little Harbor (Schoolcraft Co.) 1931-1934 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Camp Committee to Dean and Faculty of School of Natural Resources 1960 (Box 1)
- Chronological Files 1926-1946
  The Chronological Files series (.3 linear ft.) consists of 16 folders arranged chronologically that document the annual camp sessions from 1929 to 1946 (with the exception of 1936 and 1937). The folders consist of a variety of materials, the majority of which is correspondence of Camp Director Professor Robert Craig, Jr., much of it with Samuel Trask Dana, then dean of the School of Forestry and Conservation. Other materials found in this series include reports and news releases about camp activities authored by Professor Craig, student information, final examinations, property inventories, blueprints of planned buildings, news clippings, and budget information. Also of interest are feature stories submitted to the Michigan Daily by volunteer student correspondents, notable for their portrayal of student life at Camp Filibert Roth.
  Professor Craig's on-site summer reports and post-session annual reports to Dean Dana offer fine outlines of the academic-administrative regimen of the camp and are the best source of information regarding camp activities.
  - 1929-1935, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - 1938-1946, 9 folders (Box 1)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series contains brochures and a newsletter entitled The Bunkhouse Porcupine.
  - Unit Publications
    - Brochures
      - Miscellaneous 1974-1984 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - The Bunkhouse Porcupine, 1930 (Box 1)
- Alumni Association
  The Alumni Association series (.3 linear feet) consists of correspondence with or about alumni and the planning of reunions. Most of the material concerns the classes of the late 1930s and early 1940s.
  - Correspondence
    - Class of 1935 1985 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1936 1986 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1937 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1938 1989 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1940 1991 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1941 1991 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1942 1992 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1943 1993 (Box 3)
  - Deaths circa 1969-1986 (Box 3)
  - Handbook for Secretary 1983 (Box 3)
  - Missing Alumni 1904-1970 (Box 3)
  - Brief History of Foresters Associated with the 1914 Literary Class 1964 (Box 3)
- Camp Files 1930-1971
  The Camp Files series, 1930-1971 (.3 linear feet) contains material directly relating to Camp Filibert Roth. Material such as the Camp Guide and song sheets are included with maps and architectural drawings. Also included is some class material used at the camp.
  - Architectural Drawings 1940-1942 (Box 3)
  - Camp Guide and Cookbook (Box 3)
  - Class Material 1941 (Box 3)
  - Construction Costs (Box 3)
  - Guest Book 1930-1941 (Box 3)
  - Maps
    - Undated (Box 3)
    - 1930-1945 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - "Evaluation of Camp Filibert Roth," 1972 (Box 3)
    - "University Lands Used for Instruction and Research," 1971 (Box 3)
  - Song Sheets undated (Box 3)
- Midwest Forestry Conclave 1959-1984
  The Midwest Forestry Conclave series, 1959-1984 (.1 linear feet) concerns the annual Midwest Forestry Conclave, a contest of forestry skills and games between different Midwest schools. It was hosted by the university on a rotating basis with the other participant schools. The first Conclave was held in the 1950s and information is available on each year until 1984. The only exception is 1979.
  - 1959-1978, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1980-1984 (Box 3)
  - History 1954-1986 (Box 3)
- School of Natural Resources
  The School of Natural Resources series, 1908-1986 (.2 linear feet) contains materials collected by John Carrow relating to the School of Natural Resources. Carrow's correspondence regarding a 1982 review of the School details his interest and concerns for Camp Filibert Roth. There is also a history of the department written by John Carrow for the update to the Encyclopedic Survey. Earlier published histories are found in the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources and Environment record group. Some material about Dean Samuel Trask Dana is also in this series.
  - Histories
    - "History of the School of Natural Resources for the Period 1940-1971" (Box 3)
      (Encyclopedic Survey Update)
    - "History of Activities in the Field of Natural Resources at the University of Michigan 1962-1986" (Box 3)
  - Off Campus Properties
    - Clear Creek Swamp Cutting Area Map 1949 (Box 3)
  - Review of School of Natural Resources
    - Carrow's Correspondence 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Samuel Trask Dana
    - Hall of Fame Banquet 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Clippings 1947-1978 (Box 3)
    - "Sam Dana's Michigan Life" (Box 3)
  - Spring Conclave 1978-1980 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials 1910-1985, 4.6 linear feet
  The Visual Materials series (4.6 linear ft., one outsize photo album, and one outsize folder) includes both individual black and white photographic prints and photograph albums documenting the annual camp sessions. An annual group photograph was taken each year of student, faculty, and camp staff, and most years from 1929 to 1987 can be found here. Less formal photographs of activities and camp scenes were mounted in photograph albums for the years 1929 to 1964.
  It is arranged first by subject and then chronologically. The bulk of the series relates to life at Camp Filibert Roth. It is divided into several subseries: negatives, photographs, scrapbooks and slides. The negatives and photographs subseries contain images primarily from Camp Filibert Roth from 1935 to 1985. Some images are related to the School of Natural Resources and the Alumni Association from the 1950s to the 1970s. There is also some undated material. There is some overlap between the two subseries; however not all negatives have prints and not all prints have negatives. The scrapbook subseries contains beautifully laid out books of camp photos from 1932 to 1973. The majority of the slides were taken during the Midwest Conclaves in various years. A separate box of slides was left just as Carrow had organized them and contains images of logging operations, camp life, people and trips.
  - Photograph Albums of Summer Sessions
    - 1929-1931 Photograph Album (Folder UBImum/C367)
      (outsize and located separately; call no. BImu/C367) (includes Beaver Lake and Grand Island photographs)
    - 1932-1957, 1959-1964, 28 folders of pages taken from photo albums (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Camp Scenes 1929, 1930 (Box 1)
      (2 black and white images, 1 negative; 1 photo-poster located in outsize folder, call no. UBImum/C367)
    - Group Photos of Students, Faculty, and Camp Staff
      - 1929-1932, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - 1934 (Box 1)
      - 1936 (Box 1)
      - 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1941-1948, 8 folders (Box 1)
      - 1949-1950 (Folder UBImum/C367)
      - 1951-1973, 23 folders (Box 1)
      - 1974-1977 (both Sessions I and II), 8 folders (Box 1)
      - 1978 Session II (Box 2)
      - 1979-1982 (both Sessions I and II), 8 folders (Box 2)
      - 1983 Session II (Box 2)
      - 1984-1987, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Professors Allen and Craig with dog 1930, 1 negative; 2 images black and white (Box 2)
    - Thorhaug, Astrid "Oscar" 1930, 1 negative folders; 2 images black and white (Box 2)
      (the sole female student at 1930 summer camp)
  - Negatives
    - Alumni Association
      - undated (Box 4)
      - 1965 (Box 4)
      - 1967 (Box 4)
      - 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1979 (Box 4)
      - 1984 (Box 4)
      - 1988 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
    - Award Ceremonies
      - 1978 (Box 4)
    - Camp
      - undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1935 (Box 4)
      - 1957 (Box 4)
      - 1960 (Box 4)
      - 1962 (Box 4)
      - 1964-1978, 13 folders (Box 4)
      - Sawmill Fire 1978 (Box 4)
    - Conclave
      - 1959 (Box 4)
      - 1974 (Box 4)
      - 1977 (Box 4)
    - Forests undated (Box 4)
    - Group photos of students, faculty, and camp staff
      - 1929-1944, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1954, 1956-1963 (Box 4)
    - School of Natural Resources
      - Undated (Box 4)
      - 1950 (Box 4)
      - 1954 (Box 4)
      - 1966 (Box 4)
      - George Staebler undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Alumni Association
      - Undated (Box 4)
      - 1958 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1968, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1975-1979, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1988 (Box 4)
      - 1993 (Box 4)
    - Award Ceremonies
      - 1965 (Box 4)
      - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Camp
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1935 (Box 4)
      - 1938-1942 (Box 4)
      - 1944 (Box 4)
      - 1950 (Box 4)
      - 1954 (Box 4)
      - 1958-1960, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1965-1967, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1973-1976, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - 1985 (Box 4)
      - Ice Storm Damage 1976 (Box 4)
      - Sawmill Fire 1978 (Box 4)
    - Conclave
      - undated (Box 4)
      - 1959 (Box 4)
      - 1974 (Box 4)
      - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1979 (Box 4)
    - Deer Drive undated (Box 4)
    - Forests undated (Box 4)
    - George Washington Tree Planting circa 1934 (Box 4)
    - Group Photos of Students, Faculty, and Camp Staff
      - 1937 (Box 4)
      - 1940 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Session II) (Box 4)
      - Index 1942-1946 (Box 4)
    - International Academy of Foresters Association Banquet 1962 (Box 4)
    - School of Natural Resources
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1944-1950 (Box 5)
      - 1956 (Box 5)
      - 1965-1969, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Award Ceremonies
        - Undated (Box 5)
        - 1978 (Box 5)
      - Retirement Parties 1979 (Box 5)
      - Samuel Trask Dana
        - Undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - 1937-1967 (Box 5)
        - 1973 (Box 5)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - George Staebler undated (Box 5)
      - Students 1937 (Box 5)
    - Sturgeon River 1976 (Box 5)
    - Trip to Alaska 1960 (Box 5)
    - Trip to Ringold undated (Box 5)
  - Slides
    - Carrow Slides, 1 slide box
      - Long Wood Methods of Logging (Box 5)
      - Skid Forward and Load (Box 5)
      - Short Wood Methods of Logging (Box 5)
      - Load Haul and Unload (Box 5)
      - Cable Logging (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Trips (Box 5)
        - Sugar Project (Box 5)
        - Forest Survey (Box 5)
        - People and Trips (Box 5)
        - Camp Filibert Roth (Box 5)
    - Camp
      - 1937-1946 (Box 5)
      - 1948-1976, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Conclave
      - Undated (Box 5)
      - 1961 (Box 5)
      - 1963, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1975 (Box 5)
    - Ottawa N.F. 1950-1964 (Box 5)
    - PEM
      - Undated (Box 5)
      - 1940-1944 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - "School of Forestry Class of 34" (Box 6)
    - "Camp Filibert Roth, 1965-1967" (Box 6)
    - "Summers at Camp Filibert Roth"
      - 1932-1937 (Box 6)
      - 1938-1941 (Box 6)
      - 1942-1947 (Box 7)
      - 1948-1958 (Box 7)
      - 1959-1964 (Box 7)
      - 1965-1973 (Box 7)